<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Life on Yi Yao Tan</title><link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/</link><description>Recent content in Life on Yi Yao Tan</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 18:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Languages</title><link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/dating/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 18:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/dating/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve known English and Mandarin bilingually since I was young and also understood Hokkien to converse with the older generation. I taught myself from zero to full working proficiency in French in 4 months (enough to read Camus, play in a sports team, talk machine learning researchers, and even go on dates! ;P). Then I studied 2 years of Russian in French during my Undergraduate. I know a bit of Italian to joke around con gli zii (my teammates) quando giochiamo a pallavolo in Oxford and in Rome. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to learn to pronounce basic devenagri/ Hindi script, annoying my friend trying to read every single sign possible in Jaipur. I used to get by with Swedish in supermarkets thanks to my half-Swedish cousin and bits of Japanese, but I no longer claim to understand both. I&amp;rsquo;m currently learning Indonesian/ Malay so back to my roots. I&amp;rsquo;ve a spaghetti of words in my head these days, but if you have good book recommendations to help me ease into any of these languages I&amp;rsquo;d be interested : D.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dating, Gale–Shapley, Optimal stopping and Poisson</title><link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/dating/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 14:32:06 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/life/dating/</guid><description>&lt;p>Often we wonder who to date: Will they be my life partner? Why is dating so hard in our 20s and 30s? The short answer is there&amp;rsquo;s no perfect matching for everyone on both sides, but most people don&amp;rsquo;t exactly understand their preferences anyways.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="galeshapley-as-a-null-model">
 as a Null Model&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Gale–Shapley&amp;rsquo;s Stable Matching Problem serves as a reasonable null model with the most generic assumptions in a binary gender population and matching. Firstly, assumes two same-sized sets of each gender oriented towards the opposite gender and each individual knows exactly their preference ranking of the opposite gender in a discrete sense, maximal self information. For simplicity we write M and F as these gender sets.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>