<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics &amp; Entrepreneurship on Yi Yao Tan</title>
    <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics &amp; Entrepreneurship on Yi Yao Tan</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:45:44 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Firstprinciplesmaths</title>
      <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/firstprinciplesmaths/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:45:44 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/firstprinciplesmaths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some of my theories and formalizations of what linguistic from business people computing tries to approximate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Doing things which don&amp;rsquo;t scale/ Good startup ideas: are startup ideas which have high uncertainty for others however low uncertainty but high probability of success for founders based on their knowledge. Not high uncertainty and low probability, because that&amp;rsquo;s just absolutely unlikely. Innovation actually happens in a fractal branching processes how vibe coding frontend can emerge from combining the known need of website builders and control of technical infrastructure for future scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B2b</title>
      <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/b2b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 12:02:14 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/b2b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;b2b-mathematics-of-why-its-so-sexy&#34;&gt;B2B Mathematics of why it&amp;rsquo;s so sexy.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people wonder if over investment of B2B is a bubble. Like why do people love it, why does Y Combinator focus on it. Why do all entreprises over the long term converge to it. I have four theories:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Locality of information at entreprise scale, to build something and a fitting product for an entreprise is really hard and even to discover a tool which is perfect for the entreprise is really hard, communication is like square cube law if square was the surface area of the size of the entreprise, to route something to an entreprise which fits it will scale even harder, which signifies the importances of sales and stickiness of the product.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of startups</title>
      <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/startup-physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:50:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/startup-physics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-topological-view-of-the-world&#34;&gt;1. The Topological View of the World&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We exist socially, experience-wise, and physically on a &lt;em&gt;topology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;We operate in &lt;em&gt;cognitive bios&lt;/em&gt; where opinions are actually strong local views.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Understanding locality bias and thinking in distances helps us view things in perspectives&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-the-ai-bubble-phenomenon&#34;&gt;2. The “AI Bubble” Phenomenon&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Big tech and AI employees actually self selected, socially collaborative filtered for their niche.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The things the say about AGI and ASI are from the sum of their experiences. In a sense the ultimateness comes from their experiences so far. Software engineering is gone etc. etc. (which is conditioned on their notion of the &amp;ldquo;Software Engineering that they experienced has changed&amp;rdquo; phrasing on what is concrete and truly (real) sense)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People outside the industry haven&amp;rsquo;t seen directly the benefits of productivity except for note taking and call it an AI bubble.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The inability for the two groups to understand each other is due to semantical, experience, and social level distances between them. Which can be analogously said as a &amp;ldquo;Resolution limit.&amp;rdquo; Objects far away naturally look small and insignificant.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-this-topological-distance-applied-to-startups&#34;&gt;3. This Topological Distance Applied to Startups&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Analogously startup opinions and their unique value proposition can be their moat that the societal-consensus distance is far enough from things of scale that are insignificant to the incumbents by this resolution limit. It&amp;rsquo;s what &amp;ldquo;we call doing things that don&amp;rsquo;t scale&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The amount of value in the world is always expanding, houses are always created more than destroyed, items, cars, new technology and additive and thus expanding the edges/ frontiers always have new and unique value propositions and hence space for new startups.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What seems easy on surface might also be much harder when we approach the problem due to the this resolution limit which is why companies shouldn&amp;rsquo;t worry or mind themselves too much with copying another competitor if they have a unique value/ opinion on a design.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The design and business decisions of the companies are actually path dependent of the values and experiences. Point 2 of not worrying about competition.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-economics-of-innovation&#34;&gt;4. Economics of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the Monetary sense: Countries print trillions of dollars into the economy every year. Approximately new value added into the world, inflation is actually a function of many gradients such as inequality of local value flow, for example certain industries growing to be more productive than others yet the value to humans per item hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed as fast locally, Baumol Effect describes this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Interesting to read: 2025 Nobel Prize economics in Innovation Driven Economics&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-startup-in-terms-of-innovation-sampling-machine&#34;&gt;5. Startup in terms of Innovation Sampling Machine&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Drawing out a confusion matrix the goal of a startup is to sample as many True Positives, where Sampling is the act of realizing the product into concrete reality while positives is the user feedback and (PMF) in a sense.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The only &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; value they bring into the world is this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Somethings we can control: Being closer to understanding the customer (higher precision), faster sampling (higher rate),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Analogously we should not kill ideas until they&amp;rsquo;re realized but with a cost of energy trade of benefit sense.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Being curious to what could work is more fruitful for conversation of this sampling than discussing everything that won&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-local-topology-applied-to-startups&#34;&gt;6. Local Topology Applied to Startups&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;PMF is a Bifurication and diffusion process.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(0-1) Is beating the activation energy where the diffusion process of value to user &amp;gt; price paid (including UI/UX/ time/ money/ psycological convenience),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When this &amp;ldquo;Thermal Equilibrium&amp;rdquo; is broken value flows along the topology&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What we see as exponential growth is due to local community structures of whatever hiearchies grow by the number of new members added like Exponential Broadcast trees (CS Term).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Big companies have structural and branded product and cognitively clear/ branded product hiearchies: Google, Amazon.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/images/startups-way.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diagram of startup analogies&#34;&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025 Startup. Good Startup? Intuitions, mathematical perspective</title>
      <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/2025startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 13:50:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/2025startup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Status: in-construction (Sept 2025)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Philsophically: I&amp;rsquo;d hope to maximize E[E[I(Late Stage Power Law Success, Points in this Article, Early Stage) | Reader attention]]. But this is mostly for me reflectively rather than a &amp;ldquo;this is correct piece&amp;rdquo; as I&amp;rsquo;m constantly trying to revise it as I&amp;rsquo;m doing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2025 seems to have brought a lot of confusion to the way tech builds startups. Perhaps vibe-coding and automation has made us re-question the need for technical founders. The short answer is no, nothing much has changed. Perhaps the exact action the what and what has, but the technicality of engineering has always been a universal constant. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s shifted into deeper tech or more AI/ML based engineering and not the tradition apps that was true to be so 5 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Good Founders</title>
      <link>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/goodfounders/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 13:50:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yiyaotan-site.vercel.app/blog/ee/goodfounders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-makes-a-good-founder&#34;&gt;What makes a good founder?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technically Strong. Comparative advantage wins technology races, economic transactions are opportunity costs/ slight disassortative in the manner. Everyone builds on top of an almost a similar absolute advantage, it&amp;rsquo;s optimal for one&amp;rsquo;s upstream suppliers. (Eg. basic access to LLMs and cloud compute is universal expectation in 2025).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-Conscious. Ability to understand nuance, high-frequency iterative self correction and alignment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Socially Intelligent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Directness, firmness, and clarity/ pragmatism of vision- People often say disagreability, however, I think it&amp;rsquo;s inaccurate to it&amp;rsquo;s cause. The ability to get something done even if people don&amp;rsquo;t understand it why it matters. Admittedly this is hard to phrase.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
